<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a gentleman in Ireland to his brother in England, relating to the concerns of Ireland in matter of trade</title>
            <author>Marvell, Andrew, 1621-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M871B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13907</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13138646</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13138646</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97958</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70661)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97958)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 426:8 or 1727:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a gentleman in Ireland to his brother in England, relating to the concerns of Ireland in matter of trade</title>
                  <author>Marvell, Andrew, 1621-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Langley Curtiss ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Andrew Marvell. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed, March 26, 1677. Roger L'Estrange."</note>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 426:8 as Wing L1385 (number cancelled in Wing 2nd ed.), and at reel 1727:5 as Wing M871B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in National Library of Scotland (Advocates') and Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  Commerce --  England.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Ireland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97958:1"/>
            <p>A
LETTER
From a GENTLEMAN in
IRELAND
To his BROTHER in
ENGLAND,
Relating to the Concerns of
IRELAND in matter of
TRADE.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licenſed,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Roger L'Estrange.</signed> 
                           <dateline>
                              <date>March 26. 1677.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed and are to be ſold by <hi>Langley Curtiſs,</hi> in
<hi>Goat-Court</hi> upon <hi>Ludgate-hill.</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97958:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97958:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Brother,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have lately received yours, wherein you give me
account of the Fall of your Rents, the Cheapneſs
of your Wools, the decay of your Manufacture in
<hi>England;</hi> and you aſcribe the cauſe of it principally
to <hi>Ireland;</hi> which is a double Melancholly to me, that
you, firſt, who are the Head of our Family, ſhould
find your ſelf ſo ſtraitned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat you cannot ſupport its
Dignity with the ſame eaſe and plenty that you did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly:
but that I, then, who have for you all the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
and tenderneſs of ſo dear a Relation, ſhould be
engaged in a Country and Intereſt oppoſite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as it
ſeems to yours, and acceſſory to your ruine, there is
nothing worſe could happen to me, then that it were
real. And yet, did I find my ſelf here in a more happy
condition, I could better reliſh your complaints, and
my opportunity of ſerving you, would extinguiſh in
me all other ſenſe of your misfortunes. I ſhould take
an innocent pride out of a younger Brothers fortunes
to ſupply the Elder. For as in Timber, the ſap de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends
in Winter, ſo it is but natural and reaſonable,
that in hard times the Branches ſhould pinch to
ſuccour the Root of the Family. But alas, the caſe with
us is far otherwiſe, ſo deſtitute of affording you help,
that we can ſcarce find our ſelves a ſubſiſtance: but ſo
abſurd is our calamity, that we labour under abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
of want in a moſt plentiful Country. And what
aggravates it the more, is, that you in <hi>England</hi> concur
to it; not by accident only, but upon judgement
and deliberation: as if you had entertained a maxime
of deſtroying us for your own preſervation, and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
off that Twig which at one time or other might
ſave you from ſinking. Your Head akes, your Heart
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97958:3"/>
trembles, your Liver ulcerates; yet all your Diſeaſes
and Diſtempers muſt be attributed to <hi>Ireland,</hi> which
lyes and ſwells, you think, like the Spleen upon the
ſide of <hi>England.</hi> Whereas, if you could cut it off, you
would fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your ſelves by the loſs of ſuch a Receptacle
much impaired, but no advantage either in your
Health or good Humour. It is you in <hi>England</hi> only,
that have been the cauſe both of your own and our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,
and have a mind, I doubt, to continue ſo. But,
that I may not ſpend your time in Recriminations
(which is the ſolace of the Deſperate) I ſhall ſtrive to
convince you of it by Reaſon (which is the Remedy of
the Curable.) And therefore I ſhall diſcourſe it with
you with that freedom which the neceſſity of the Caſe
requires, and which is moſt ſuitable to the intimacy of
our Fraternal Relation; the beſt Emblem of that Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence
which were to be wiſhed between the two
Nations for their Mutual Happineſs.</p>
            <p>And becauſe what is freſheſt in memory, doth moſt
affect the Underſtanding, I ſhall date this Argument no
further back then the Kings bleſſed Reſtauration: that
<hi>Caroline</hi> period, from which, as a ſecond Creation of
our leſſer world, it were proper to reckon a New Stile;
and, were it of the ſame labour, to have reformed both
the Times and the Calendar. That ſeaſonable return
had filled all minds with ſo general a ſatisfaction, that
it ſeemed no man had cauſe, or leiſure, or inclination
to wiſh worſe to others, or themſelves better. And as
the reſt, ſo we in <hi>Ireland</hi> (happy becauſe contented)
lived in a condition tolerable to our ſelves, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable
to <hi>England.</hi> For without buſie proſpects of
greater advantage, we gave our ſelves in a manner
wholly to that harmleſs and primitive courſe of breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Cattel; which we tranſported to you, and ſold at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97958:3"/>
eaſie rates in your Markets: wherein we had but that
ſingle, you a manifold profit; both in the Groſs, by
ſtocking your Grounds therewith to feed them; and in
the Retail, by thoſe ſeveral Commodities that ariſe in
the Slaughter; the Tallow, the Victual, the Hides, and
the Fleeces, all which turned to account of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective
Trades therein concerned. And, which is yet
more weighty to conſider, we did not hereby drain
away your Money to hoard it up, or brood upon it in
<hi>Ireland:</hi> but very ſimply and honeſtly, as ſoon as we
had received it with one hand, we laid it out again
with the other, with you for your Manufactures, or for
the Foreign Commodities of which you were our Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants;
or elſe it went to furniſh ſuch of our Nobility
as reſided in your Court for their Expences. And it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
much ſubtilty to invent what more you could
have deſired of us, and how either in Commerce we
could be more ſubſervient, or in Policy we could be
more dependent upon you, then by this means we were
rendred, without attempting or dreaming on our ſide
of any further intercourſe: all the benefit of <hi>Ireland</hi>
redounding to you, while to us there remained no
more but a bare livelihood. And yet after ſome years
that things had continued on in this tenour, all on a
ſudden, and, if we were rightly informed, not without
ſome repugnance at firſt in His Majeſty, the Importation
of our <hi>Iriſh</hi> Cattel is by Act of Parliament prohibited.
And (to clench it the faſter, and to ſet (if I may ſo
ſay) a Spell upon His Majeſties Power and Prudence,
leſt he might upon occaſion redreſs it for the future)
it is in a Magical and ſevere term of Law declared to
be a publick Nuſance. What could be the reaſon, it is
not for me to conjecture, much leſs to determine. But
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97958:4"/>
whatſoever leſs and inviſible Spring might, as is uſual in
other great affairs, animate this motion, it cannot be
otherwiſe in ſo numerous and prudent an Aſſembly, ſo
involved in the Intereſt of their Country, and ſenſible
of their own, but it muſt have been repreſented under
the moſt ſpecious, colourable, and neceſſary Arguments;
That by this Importation, your own breed of Cattel
decayed, your Markets were glutted, and your Rents
ſtarved. Wherein give me leave to ſay, that it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
to you as with men who having run themſelves
out, do ſet up late for Frugality; they entertain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
with every Project that firſt preſents it ſelf, and
what is next, does always ſeem moſt reaſonable. For
admitting that ſome of your Counties might be preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced
by the Importation of our Cattel, yet whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
profit accrued to others by it, did, upon the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
neceſſities of all, circle into the common Stock of
your Nation. And it ſeems to me, that whatſoever
private Obligation a Parliament-man hath to the place
where he is elected; yet, when once he comes to ſit,
his Truſt and his Mind is inlarged, and he does no more
conſider himſelf as the Polititian of a Shire, or the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot
of a Borough, but as a Repreſenter of the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality.
Whereas otherwiſe, if any County, one or more,
chance to be more fertile then other in Members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
and they Act by ſuch narrow Meaſures; the
Deciſion would be by Multitude, not by Reaſon; Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick
would be Logick, and the greater Herd, as
among Cattel, would carry it. You beſt know how that
matter went who are one of them; and however your
opinion ſtand in other things as to us in <hi>Ireland;</hi> yet I
need not Divine your thoughts on this Queſtion, ſerving
as you do for—, and ſo the Bias of your Intereſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97958:4"/>
there corroborating the general rectitude of your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
And if the buſineſs were now to tell Counties,
I have been lately aſſured by ſome from <hi>England,</hi> that
thoſe Counties that find themſelves not benefited, and
thoſe that are really aggrieved by this Act, do by this
time upon Experiment and ſecond thoughts, make up
the greateſt party. For, if we account like Merchants
by Profit and Loſs, all the Profit that can be made by
this Act, returns only to ſuch Counties which are proper
for Breeding, or the deeper Feeding of Cattel of your
own growth; whereby they do but raiſe the price upon
their Neighbours, and Monopolize the reſt of your
Nation. Theſe other in the mean time have their
Grounds thrown up into their own hands, which uſed to
be ſtock'd with our leſſer Cattel, that ſerved them, as ſmall
Money does poor People, for Change at the Market.
And your whole Nation hath hereby loſt in great
meaſure the Vent of their Home and Foreign Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities
to <hi>Ireland,</hi> and wholly the increaſing Product to
you of our Cattel <hi>in ſpecie.</hi> But as to the Political point,
you did herein, as much as in you then was, cut off all
that ſtronger, as more Natural dependance of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
upon yours, and neceſſitate your ſelves to govern
it rather by the force of Authority, then by the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ential
benignity of Intereſt. It were too tragical to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
to you the ſurprize and aſtoniſhment with which
the firſt News of that Act ſeized and affected us. Our
condition did contrarily reſemble his in the Fable, who
ſaw every thing turn'd into Gold that he ſhould have
fed upon, but we could only feed upon that, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
we converted into Money. It may beſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
and conceived by the decrying of Coin, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
he that was one day Maſter, as he imagined, of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97958:5"/>
great Wealth, finds the next morning nothing but an
unvaluable lump, wherein to contemplate his Poverty.
What was to be done in this exigent? when we were
reduced to the perfect ſtate of <hi>Boccaneers,</hi> to kill Cows
and ſurfeit our ſelves on the Carkaſſes, that we might
ſell the Hides to the next charitable Foreigner that
chanced to viſit us.</p>
            <p>Being thus to begin the world again, and conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to look out for a new way to ſuſtain Nature, we took
councel of neceſſity. Our Commodities out of which
we could ſubſiſt, were either our Corn, our greater
Cattel, or our Sheep. For the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Corn, it could
ſerve us only to Market with among our ſelves; being
by reaſon of the Climate, not ſo large, firm and dry a
Grain, that it ſhould be proper for Tranſportation:
And conſequently we Plowed no more then might
ſerve us yearly from hand to mouth for our own ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
For our Cattel, we continued the breeding of
them, and imployed part of our grounds to feed them:
Finding, for the proportion, more Advantage by Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alling
it out to Foreigners, then what we had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
by their Whole-ſale in <hi>England.</hi> But that Vent
was nothing equal to what thoſe Tracts of Land, that
lay idle before us would have furniſhed: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
we betook our ſelves more generally to the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
of Sheep, in which you know, how numerous
Flocks, and wide Paſtures are managed by one Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd.
So that this courſe did beſt ſuit with our Purſe,
that could not anſwer any more expenſive profit; and
with our Diſpoſitions, that are not made for Laborious
improvements; and with your Jealouſie, who interpret
our induſtry as Theft, and that we defraud you as oft
as we make the leaſt attempt to work out an honeſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97958:5"/>
Living. So that the Wool now was the onely thing
that we had to reſt upon: And you were provided
with ſufficient Act of Parliament to be the onely
Mart for it: It being made Felony to Tranſport it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
forain parts; and Confiſcation to Import it to you,
otherwiſe than crude and unmanufactur'd. And yet,
having thus again patched up a ſlender Subſiſtence and
method of being, we had re-compoſed our ſelves, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying
Poverty and Eaſe, and leading an <hi>Arcadian</hi>-life,
ſolaced among the Sheep with our Paſtorals. We had
left muttering any more at your Act againſt <hi>Iriſh</hi>-Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,
and onely ſmiled, as in a Triumph, not of Malice, but
of Reaſon, to ſee that you were now the perſons agrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved;
and if not yet convinced of the cauſe, yet labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
under the effects of it. For, whereas ſome Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
onely could complain of our Cattle, the cheap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s
of Wools was become a general incommodity to your
whole Nation. For, I believe, as you were ready e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
to imagine, that by importing upon you all the
Wools of this Kingdom, yours were partly choaked; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
more of your own upon your hands already, than, in
the preſent ſtate of Trade thorough the World, your
own Manufactors could work, or your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>chants vend
beyond Sea. Although, we paying the King's and
Lieutenant's Duty, which is at leaſt Two ſhillings for
every Stone, beſide the fraught of the Ships that bring
it over, and the other charges of Factorage and Market,
are competently guarded from the danger of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling
you. For, by this means it is eaſie to compute,
that in reſpect to your Wools, ours are ſold at that which
Merchants call Fifty <hi>per Cent.</hi> diſadvantage. Yet, as the
Trade of our Cattle injured you before, ſo now our
Wools grow toward a Nuiſance: what was lawful for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97958:6"/>
us and profitable to you, you prohibited; what you
conſtrain us to, you accuſe: you are neither well full
nor faſting; I know not what you would have, unleſs
you could furniſh us with a breed of Sheep that bore
no fleeces. Is it not the ſame, that thoſe fleeces bear no
price? But though thoſe Gentlemen among you whoſe
Rents depend much upon that product, do doubtleſs
finde their Eſtates by the late cheapneſs of Wool much
reduced; yet I ſhall, ere I cloſe this Letter, ſhew you
that our <hi>Iriſh</hi>-wool is the leaſt acceſſory to it. And
however, your Kingdom doth ſo abound with native
Commodities (which, were you not ſo in love with the
forain, would multiply to you in Treaſure and Bullion)
that you might well, or much better than we, diſpence
with the common calamity upon that Trade, who have
ſo many more to truſt to: Whereas this is in a manner
the onely one that is left us, and that too fails us. For
it is not to be preſum'd that, while your own Wool ſells
not, you will out of good nature prefer ours at a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket:
Nor that you are ſo new-fangled, as much ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
as you make us, that you will enquire out for <hi>la
Lained' Irlande,</hi> and make it your mode to wear it. But
it remain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eer Drug, although you are thoſe that
will be the Ingroſſers. In this condition, miſerable to
our ſelves, and yet ſubject to your envy, what can be
propounded for our relief, or toward your ſatisfaction?
Shall we ſteal our Wool beyond Sea? which yet were
but to ſteal our own goods; that you will ſay would
be a greater prejudice to you. Shall we manufacture it
at home? That, although a double benefit to us, would
ſeem to you a double inconvenience. And yet there is
no third way left, unleſs, like your Spiders, to weave out
our own Bowels.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97958:6"/>
And here it may not be amiſs to inform you, ſomething
better than I perceive you are at preſent, concerning
the ſtate of our Manufac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re in <hi>Ireland:</hi> not ſo much
becauſe it is in it ſelf grown ſo conſiderable that it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
mention, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of all Virtues, Induſtry is the laſt
of which you will have cauſe to accuſe us) as by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
it hath of late made a great noiſe with you, as things
uſually do that are moſt empty. About ten or twelve
years ago (before your Act againſt the Iriſh Cattle)
ſome Weſtern Cloathiers finding, ſo early, and upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
reaſons than are now ſuborned, that Trade decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
and many of them reduced to extream Poverty, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved
themſelves and their Families over into <hi>Ireland;</hi>
invited by the cheapneſs there of Wool and of Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.
Theſe erected then a Manufactory (great in
reſpect to <hi>Ireland)</hi> at <hi>Dublin,</hi> which hath been carried
on ever ſince, and increaſes dayly. There came alſo
over, much about the ſame time, Sixty Families from
<hi>Holland,</hi> ſetting up another at <hi>Lymerick;</hi> which by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
of the ſucceeding Wars decayed. But after
theſe, more of the Engliſh Cloathiers came and fixed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<hi>Corke</hi> and <hi>Kinſale,</hi> where they continue, and are
grown not inconſiderable. Some <hi>French</hi> have ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted
to <hi>Waterford,</hi> to make Druggets there, and other
Commodities of their faſhion. And about a year or
two ago, ſome Merchants of <hi>London</hi> raiſed another Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture
at <hi>Clonmel,</hi> managing it by their Agents.
Some ſmall Attempts of the like nature may be met with
here and there in the Countries, but not worth ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
of. Theſe are the Crimes of which we are gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y
before any Law to prohibit us: it were more allowable
to plant Poyſon than Manufacture with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and we lie
it ſeems under ſuch an Obloquy and Clamo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97958:7"/>
as far as I can judge by your Letter, you alſo liſten to)
that, as to import our Cattle to you is a Nuiſance, and
to export our Wools is Felon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; ſo, by gradation, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
here a Manufacture ought to be no leſs than Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
And yet there is more Cry than Wool in all this
matter: For I dare, and do aſſure you, that, modeſtly
ſpeaking, the whole quantity of what we work up in
<hi>Ireland,</hi> amounts not to the half of what any one Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing-County
in <hi>England.</hi> Of what Importance Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture
is to us, appears more than ſufficiently by this
jealouſie of it that you have conceived, and by that Life
which ſo ſmall but active a Particle inſinuates into this
poor and idle Body of a Nation. If it were Promoted
as carefully as it is Diſcouraged, it would make his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's
Revenue here riſe with more Eaſe to the Subject,
and proportionably increaſe it for the future. It would
repleniſh the Country with People, raiſe the price of
our Lands, and wear off the Barbarity of the common
<hi>Iriſh,</hi> when once they were inured to Labour: For In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry
is the firſt ſtep to Civility, and the ſecureſt pledge
to Government; thoſe that will take pains for their
own living, being the leaſt inclined to invade anothers
Propriety. If thoſe that are the Heads of ſuch Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings
reſide with you in <hi>England,</hi> all the Product they
ſhould make here, would return over to you into the
common Stock of your Nation: If they do not, but
reſide with us, we indeed receive the Advantages above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned;
but to you there is no other difference, than
that you are Rich on this ſide of the water.</p>
            <p>All that can be objected reaſonably (for none, I hope
do officiouſly maligne us) is, that you are however the
neareſt Neighbours to your ſelves, and whatever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
of us, ſink or ſwim, you muſt provide that you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97958:7"/>
ſuffer not by us, either in exhauſting your People,
whereof you are already not too numerous; or by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing
your Trade, which is already much decayed.
As to the danger of depopulating you, which is the
firſt, it is a thing you can onely preſuppoſe and imagine,
but which we, were it a thing to be wiſhed, could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
hope for. God forbid (if it be lawful to make ſo
unneceſſary and vain a requeſt) that any accident or
extremity ſhould cauſe you to exchange <hi>Middleſex</hi> for
<hi>Lemſter,</hi> and prefer <hi>Dublin</hi> before <hi>London,</hi> to be the
Imperial Seat and Chamber of the Monarchy. It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
as the profit of an Huſbandman, to have his Land
full ſtock'd with Cattle; ſo of a Prince, to have his
Dominions mann'd with a proportionable complement
of People. And one of our Country-men intereſſed in
both Nations, hath therefore well calculated how much
the Publick miſſes or gains in the perſon of every In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual.
The Bodies of Men are not onely eſtimable
while living, but when dead: And, were it not to play
the Coqueten in Trade, I could demonſtrate what
prejudice the Nation receives by the burying of every
Engliſh-man beyond Sea; and how far the Smith, the
Iron-monger, the Joyner, and the Curate, with ſeveral
other Trades, are thereby damnified, and our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
advantaged. And I could then diſpute, that an
Act againſt Oaken Coffins were no leſs neceſſary at
home for preſerving your Timber, than that for Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel-ſhrowds
was for the incouragement of your Woollen
Manufacture. But if this of the Dead ſeems ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
to you, pardon me if I ſay, that were we not of
the two the more melancholy Nation, neither could
we refrain from ſmiling at this your frugality of the
Living. For, how can we think you ſerious in ſo ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culative
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97958:8"/>
and remote a Conſideration, that, as to us, it is
rather a Caſe put, than what can ever be preſumed to
fall out in practice. For, while herein you repreſent
the Weaver, who overſhooting his Shuttle into the
Wall, although a Batchelor, wet his cheeks and his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture
to think, how if his onely ſon had received
that blow, his Majeſty had loſt a Subject, and himſelf
the ſtay of his Family; you nevertheleſs at the ſame
time, and while at Peace, tranſport yearly many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands
of <hi>Engliſh</hi> to be kill'd in the Wars, and are become
the Magazine of men to your Neighbours. You do not
onely ſend out yearly ſwarms of men to your old Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
but, wanting, it ſeems, Hives for your multitude,
you do every day increaſe your new Buildings at home,
and abroad deſign new Plantations. And even your
Merchants, incorporated with others, whoſe greater
quality may ſuppoſe them to be States-men in that
particular; yet, inſtead of bringing over more Gold
from <hi>Guiny,</hi> do, as I am told, ſo inhanſe their ſole Trade of
<hi>Negroes,</hi> that your Planters, not able to go to the price,
are forced to load their Ships continually with <hi>Engliſh</hi>
Servants. And, if there were this penury of people
with you, it is probable that you would finde out
Employment for ſo many idle perſons that, as I obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
when I came laſt over, notwithſtanding thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
draughts beyond Sea, do both Natives and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainers
peſter you ſtill at home, and ſo incumber your
Streets and your High-ways, that a man of buſineſs
can ſcarce paſs without juſtling. Therefore it is time
for you to quit this Notion, which you ſo many ways
ſlight in effect, and contradict in practiſe, and in our caſe
is ſo ſingular: unleſs you will affix your inhabitants
like Trees to the Soil, and lay as ſevere an Injunction
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97958:8"/>
againſt your <hi>Engliſh</hi> mens going abroad, as that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
you have impounded our Cattle at home in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which may afford more appearance of reality is,
that our Woollen Manufactures interrupt the Vent of
yours. But I have already ſhewn you how ſlender a
quantity is wrought up with us; ſo ſmall a pittance, that
it cannot affect even your <hi>Norwich,</hi> much leſs your whole
Kingdom: nor is there yet any Law (I hope will not)
to interdict us what, if real, were ſo neceſſary. The
<hi>Dutch,</hi> the <hi>French,</hi> any Forrainer have Liberty, and make
uſe of it, to work with us; and ſhall either the <hi>Iriſh</hi> or
<hi>Engliſh</hi> of both Countries be rather debarr'd, whether
Rich from planting Manufacture, or whether Poor from
labouring it in <hi>Ireland?</hi> I know not that ever it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
into your minds to forbid your <hi>Engliſh</hi> the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing
of Land among us: and what reaſon is there
greater to hinder them from imploying their Money with
us upon any other occaſion to private and publick advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage?
But what do I inſtance in Land, a thing the moſt
improbable; and to which, as it ſtands with us, the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi>
can at preſent have no temptation? when, beſide
the novelty, weakneſs, and mutability of Titles, every
thing from which the profit might reſult, is rendred ſo
incommodious to us, and unpracticable, that as the
Tenant hath onely his Labour for his Pains, ſo the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſer,
inſtead of Rent, can only have his Land for his
Money. Therefore I ſubmit it to you to chuſe any more
particular and proper inſtance (if ſuch there be) where
<hi>Engliſh</hi> mens Eſtates lie under ſuch a perpetual Tuition,
and others may adminiſter to him that is yet living. But
this Clamour hath ſo little of a publick ſpirit in it, that
it ſavours rather of that envy which is among little Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificers,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97958:9"/>
or meaner Merchants that trade or factor in the
ſame Commodity: For there is indeed no man but doth
in ſome ſort prejudice another; no Trade but is to the
detriment of another Trade in ſome meaſure: yet theſe
are all reconciled in the publick Convenience or Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity;
otherwiſe every County, every Company, every
Member would ſtand in anothers way, and there ſhould
be no end of Diviſibility. But, if you were in earneſt,
methinks it would better require your good Huſbandry
and Inſpection to rectifie thoſe, whether Trades or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
that ſuck out your very blood, tranſvaſating for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain
Juyces into your Veins; and that, while they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
your Treaſure and Bullion, prey upon your Vitals.
And to diſcover ſuch others, who, under the quality of
Engliſh Merchants, are, as is ſaid, but Factors for Aliens,
and dayly ſpirit away the Wealth and Strength of your
Nation beyond Sea. But however you judge and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
of your Domeſtick Affairs, ſuffer not your ſelves, in
regard of us, to be impoſed on by falſe ſuggeſtions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
your own and our Intereſt.</p>
            <p>For the deadneſs of your Manufactures, as well as
ours, proceeds not from their interfering with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
but from much differing cauſes, wherein it may
befit you, firſt to conſider (for I will not, to the diſ-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
of ſo many worthy Merchants, affirm what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported
at this diſtance) whether ſeveral of thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies
that are intruſted and impower'd with the ſole
Trade of your home-bred Commodities in remote Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions,
do not for their more exceſſive advantage, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear
to buy up that quantity which ſo great a part of
the world as lies ſtretch'd out in their Patents, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſited
in their Traffick, would take off, at a more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate
profit. And whether they do not, for what
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97958:9"/>
Quantity they do utter, methodize their buying ſo
artificially, to ſuch times, conditions, and reſtrictive
regulations, practiſing upon the Manufactors neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
that the poor men lie at the Merchants mercy,
and their goods lie ſo long upon their hands, till
they are forced to receive any rate from the ſingle Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's
diſcretion. For, whether it be ſo or no in this
particular, there is that general malignity in Commerce,
that the rich Buyer does ſet the Dice always upon the
neceſſitous Seller: as in the moſt plentiful years of Corn,
the Ingroſſer never thinks the Market low enough.
But a more evident and certain reaſon of yours and
our conſuming for want of Conſumption, is the Wars,
with which formerly and of later years, <hi>Europe</hi> has ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
been infeſted. So that in moſt parts thereof,
which were uſually ſupplied from you, the people have
been much impoveriſhed, and thereby neceſſitated to be
their own Clothiers firſt, and from thence enabled, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry
increaſing, ſome of them to furniſh their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.
And to this ſeveral of your own Subjects have
concurred, who either not finding themſelves well and
eaſie at home, or inticed over by greater profit, have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed
Forainers in the whole myſtery of Cloathing,
till they now have made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Staple Commodity, and
out-do yours for perfection, and, what between their
finer and courſer Manufactures, can both over and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ſell
you at any Market; where you too, that were
the ſole Merchants, do often condeſcend to be their
Chapmen. Thus by the reciprocation of humane af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,
that Trade which the Wars, upon the Forainers
refuge with you, firſt introduced, is upon occaſion of
the Wars revolved back again, and the Drapery reſtored
to them in great meaſure, even by means of your own
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97958:10"/>
But the grand ſpring of this whole matter lies in
<hi>France.</hi> That King is a moſt vigilant and potent Prince,
ſtrong in Arms, in Councel, in Treaſure, and in People,
and who meaſures Juſtice by his Intereſt. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly,
ever ſince he manifeſted himſelf, and aſſumed the
whole direction of his own affairs, he hath made war to
all <hi>Europe:</hi> with his Sword, againſt his Enemies; but
againſt his Friends, (and Enemies alſo) by Traffique;
which is indeed, as the more juſt, ſo the moſt effectual
way of deſtroying them. But, among all, none hath
on this latter account more ſuffered than the Subjects of
<hi>England.</hi> For, beſide the Wines, which we purchaſe at
moſt exceſſive rates, and for the moſt part with pure
Money, (although, if it pleaſed the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
there might more generous Wines and upon bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
terms be imported from <hi>Italy</hi> and the <hi>Mediterranean)</hi>
and beſide thoſe Trinkets, of which we are ſo fond,
and to the making of which the <hi>French</hi> Genius was
formerly moſt adapted: He hath, now for many years,
applied his people to the more ſolid Trades of Cloath,
Silk, and Stuffs, indeed of all things valuable; embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
in effect, or in projection, the univerſal Monarchy of
Commerce. Never did any Prince, except our own,
addict himſelf ſo wholly to the encouragement of
Trade and Navigation. Therefore he hath not onely
promoted the building of Merchants-ſhips, to carry in
and out; but provided himſelf alſo of a formidable
Navy, fit to juſtifie whatſoever he ſhall think reaſon to
attempt. He hath both trained up his own Subjects to
Sea, which before they nauſeated, and allured over great
numbers of your beſt Mariners into his ſervice. To
this, he hath either wholly prohibited<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or which is tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamount,
laid ſo exceſſive Impoſitions upon all <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:97958:10"/>
Manufactures, and other Merchandizes which were
vendible there, that they are in a manner totally exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
and you have no Commodity to exchange with,
but whatever you have of his (and have it you will
whatſoever it coſt you) muſt be bought with the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.
Inſomuch, that I have ſeen here a particular, drawn
up as 'tis ſaid in your Parliament, wherein they compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
beſide the <hi>Lucrum ceſſans,</hi> that your Nation ſuſtains a
clear loſs of <hi>Eleven hundred thouſand pounds</hi> yearly by
the <hi>French</hi> Trade. And what would any private man's
Eſtate with ſuch Huſbandry come to in a ſhort period?
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eby the <hi>French,</hi> that were before, at beſt, but the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>llainers of <hi>Europe,</hi> are now become, or pretend to be,
the Cape-merchants; and their King gives, not onely
the Mode, but the Garment to all Chriſtendome, and
the World puts it ſelf into his Livery at their own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences.
Well may you in <hi>England</hi> complain of the
death rather than deadneſs of your Manufacture, when
from this cauſe it receives ſuch an obſtruction, even to
ſuffocation, when you are not onely deprived of that
general and gainful vent that you had formerly in <hi>France</hi>
it ſelf, but in all other places where you traffique you
meet the <hi>French</hi> now at every turn; and the Forrain
Poſt brings News from all parts that they are before you,
and have under-ſold you in the ſame Commodities.</p>
            <p>And to this Diſeaſe ſo mortal, and which it is beyond
any private man to remedy, your ſelves do more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
contribute, by thoſe vaſt quantities of Wool
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich, they tell us here, are daily, and now more than ever
tranſported for <hi>France;</hi> (a thing that you always prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,
but it ſeems you always tolerate) ſo that in effect <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
is ſtill no leſs your Staple than while it was formerly
under the Engliſh Dominion. I will not excuſe our ſelves
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97958:11"/>
in <hi>Ireland</hi> from the ſame Crime, although in leſs propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
For whereſoever any Commodity is ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pent up,
as with us, it will force it ſelf a vent one way or other.
But you have, as I hear, a <hi>Militia,</hi> that in defiance
of all Authority, convoy their Caravans of Wool
to the Shallop with ſuch a ſtrength, that your Officers
dare not offend them: while whatſoever we do of that
kind, is more modeſt; and whereſoe're it loſes its way
afterwards at Sea, it is firſt entred for <hi>England,</hi> and
pays, as I told you before, both the King's Duty, and
that to the Lord-Lieutenant, for Licenſe: So that, as we
cannot Trade, ſo neither can we Steal with you on equal
terms.</p>
            <p>By this time I hope you are ſatisfied and convinced,
that <hi>Ireland</hi> deſerves not your Complaint, but your
Pity: and that thoſe things which ſome have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
to us, are but the common Calamity of both
Nations, occaſioned by the Flux of Humane Affairs,
and Accidents of the preſent Conjuncture thorow <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope:</hi>
and therefore that you will not only conſult how
to redreſs our common Grievances, but that you will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
remedy thoſe more particular Preſſures that we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
by or under you. For <hi>Ireland</hi> is indeed a Country
ſcituate with great advantage for Commerce, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
toward the Weſtern and Southern Navigation.
The Ports are many, and of the moſt capable and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious.
The Soil is fertile, and where not, yet pregnant,
in many places with Minerals, and elſewhere large and
well grown Woods, fit to be ſhaped out into Navies;
with ſuch convenience for building, that I have often
wondred how, in ſuch ſcarcity of Timber, you have
not ſometimes thought of having one <hi>Chatham</hi> at leaſt
in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97958:11"/>
Nature has indeed been kinde to us, were You ſo
likewiſe. But you prohibit our Cattel, you reſtrain
our Wool; our Manufacture is intolerable; you forbid
our Trading with any Forreign Commodities in your
own Plantations: what we buy there, we muſt enter
in <hi>England;</hi> and before we land it, muſt make a ſecond
and more dangerous Voyage, to pay you double Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms.
We are in all things, indeed, treated by you
like, or worſe than Aliens. In the mean time, we pay
Quit-rents, Chimney-money, Exciſe, Cuſtoms; and
have been as ready as you to Supply his Majeſtie upon
occaſions with Taxes extraordinary. Nor yet is the
Revenue eaſier to us, by being collected by Farmers.</p>
            <p>It would require an exquiſite memory, to tell you
of any late Act of State relating to <hi>Ireland,</hi> that hath
not, one way or other, turn'd to our prejudice. And
yet, though unhappie, we are Conſtant; nor hath it
ever yet been in your power to diſoblige our Affection,
much leſs our Loyalty. But I can anſwer for my ſelf:
who is he that can enter a perpetual Guaranty for a
whole Kingdom? The moſt Sacred Tyes will not hold,
when worn out continually by ill uſage. How inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
it is to a Woman to be Debauched, if ſhe finde not
the Contents of Marriage! eſpecially if ſhe be Idle, have
entertained former correſpondence with one that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
more potent, and who promiſes to maintain her in
an higher Equipage. If any of your Neighbours
ſhould be at leaſure to apply both Force and Courtſhip
to this Kingdom when it were in ill humour, it muſt
be of an extraordinary Vertue to reſiſt the Temptation:
and ſhould he gain its Good-will, he would make you
pay afterwards what Alimony he pleaſed. You might
then too late compute how neceſſary it had been to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97958:12"/>
preſerve and cheriſh it by all means poſſible: what da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,
what diminution you receive both in your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
and Revenue. Another would know how to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove,
and againſt your ſelves, thoſe Advantages that
you have ſlighted: and this Iſland which, partly by the
Natural, but more by its Political Scituation, lies like a
Mole ſit to ſhield you from Forreign Winds, to repel the
Neighbouring Seas from breaking in upon you, and to
make <hi>England</hi> the moſt quiet Station of all <hi>Europe, (In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſula
Portum efficit)</hi> would in a Strangers power ſerve
him as a Bridge to land upon you more commodiouſly.
For it is not ſo old as true a Saw, That <hi>He who will win</hi>
England, <hi>must begin with</hi> Ireland.</p>
            <p>In concluſion, the ſame aſpect that <hi>Sicily</hi> has to <hi>Italy,</hi>
that, in all Parallels, hath <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>England:</hi> and it
concerns your utmoſt care that you govern it not after
the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> manner, leſt you prepare it to Revolt unto
another Dominion. Therefore I would humbly adviſe
you, Brother, in particular, no more to look upon us
(which is the Common Errour) as a diſtinct, but as a
conjunct Intereſt and People; and to do your part,
what we are now rather in ſhew, to Conſolidate us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
into your own Subſtance. You have told me, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
formerly, how many miles of barren Hills the
Citie of <hi>Genoua</hi> hath, at vaſt expence, taken into their
Fortifications; with that Inſcription at the Entrance:
<hi>Ne munimenta Naturae Hostis verteret in Pericula.</hi> But
what Method to uſe in particular, I am not capable to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineate;
nor were I, yet neither am I proper to preſcribe
to your Parliamentary prudence. For even Phyſicians,
when ſick, diſtruſt their own Skill, and ſubmit to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's
Counſel.</p>
            <p>Whether you will think ſit to reverſe your Act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97958:12"/>
our Cattel, I know not; nor can I anſwer for
the Effect that it would produce. But I have often
obſerved how gladly Waters that have been diverted
return and fall again into their former Chanel.</p>
            <p>That you ſhould make any Act to encourage Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture
with us, is what can ſcarce be expected; but I
hope you will make none to diſcourage it. For, as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
no Phyſician to tell, that to keep a man warm is
good againſt a Cold; ſo I, though no Politician, dare
ſay in general, that it concerns you to uſe us kindly, and
to indulge us in all things that tend to Civilize, Culti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate,
and People this Nation; whereby you will or may
have, within ten hours ſail of you, a Plantation worth all
thoſe other that weaken you at ſo great a diſtance, while
we ſhould always be at hand, and within call, not more
ready to defend our ſelves than you, upon the firſt inſult
of an Enemy. By how much you have uſed us to expect
leſs, the leſs will oblige us. We will allow you eaſily to
make, what we are, younger Brothers of us; onely uſe
us as Brethren, not as Slaves. For it is an equal oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
to command men to make Brick without Straw,
and where there is both Brick and Straw to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
it. The moſt adequate Preſident whereby I can
repreſent to you both our Conditions, and what to do
in our caſe, is that of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> in the 13th of
<hi>Geneſis. Abraham</hi> was, like you, <hi>very rich in Cattle, in
Silver, and in Gold:</hi> but <hi>Lot</hi> had onely <hi>Flocks and
Herds, and Tents.</hi> And, <hi>as they journyed, their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as ſo great, that they could not dwell together:
but there was a ſtrife between the Herdſmen of Abraham's
cattle and the Herdſmen of Lot's cattle; and the Canaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
and the Perizzite dwelled then in the land. And
Abraham ſaid unto Lot, Let there be no ſtrife, I pray thee,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97958:13"/>
betwixt me and thee,</hi> and <hi>between my Herdſmen and thy
Herdſmen, for we are Brethren. Is not the whole land
before us? If thou wilt go to the left hand, I will go to
the right; and if thou depart to the right hand, then will,
I go to the left. And Lot lifted up his eyes and beheld all
the plain of Jordan, that it was well watered every where,
and Lot choſe him all the plain of Jordan. Abraham
dwelt in the land of Canaan.</hi> The Text is ſo plain, and
applies it ſelf ſo eaſily betwixt us, that it needs no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary.
Onely <hi>Abraham</hi> here was the Elder Brother;
but, being ſeveral ways the richer, ſeems therefore, out
of a natural equity and condeſcention, to have left the
choice to <hi>Lot,</hi> who was the Son of the Younger, and had
nothing but his Flocks and Herds to truſt to. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
we ſhall willingly ſubmit to the Order of Nature and
of our Government, deſiring you to chuſe for us. And
ſo God direct you in all your Councils, to His Glory, the
Honour of His Majeſtie, and to the Wealth and Welfare
of both Nations: which is the conſtant Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Brother,</salute>

               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant,
and moſt affectionate Brother.</signed> 
               <dateline>Dublin, <date>Jan. 15.
1676/7.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
